<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>trigger on zixia</title><link>/en/trigger/</link><description>Recent content in trigger on zixia</description><generator>Hugo -- 0.155.0</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 13:20:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/en/trigger/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Do Chinese People Eat Dogs? — The Arrogance and Double Standards of Western Civilization</title><link>/en/do-chinese-people-eat-dogs-the-arrogance-and-double-standards-of-western-civilization/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2026 13:20:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/do-chinese-people-eat-dogs-the-arrogance-and-double-standards-of-western-civilization/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="do-chinese-people-eat-dogs--the-arrogance-and-double-standards-of-western-civilization"&gt;Do Chinese People Eat Dogs? — The Arrogance and Double Standards of Western Civilization&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Living abroad, whenever I&amp;rsquo;m at a party and the conversation gets lively, there are always a few people, with a sense of &amp;lsquo;higher civilization&amp;rsquo; superiority, who feign innocence and ask me:
&amp;ldquo;Do Chinese people eat dogs?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their eyes often hold three parts curiosity and seven parts judgment, as if a nod from me would instantly devolve me from a modern human into a blood-drinking barbarian. To this, I no longer rush to explain. Instead, I smile and ask back:
&amp;ldquo;Do you drink milk? Do you eat veal?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>A Comprehensive Comparison of Basic Education in Spain: The Truth Chinese Parents Should Know</title><link>/en/a-comprehensive-comparison-of-basic-education-in-spain-the-truth-chinese-parents-should-know/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/a-comprehensive-comparison-of-basic-education-in-spain-the-truth-chinese-parents-should-know/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Spain has a system of free and compulsory education from ages 6 to 16, covering 6 years of primary school and 4 years of secondary school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="-school-hours-and-tuition-differences"&gt;📚 School Hours and Tuition Differences&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spanish Public Schools&lt;/strong&gt;: School hours are from 9:00 AM to 2:00 PM, with 4 classes per day. They are free of charge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spanish Private and International Schools&lt;/strong&gt;: School hours are typically from 9:00 AM to 4:00 PM, with 6 classes per day.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The median tuition for private schools is approximately €6,000/year (about 50,000 RMB).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;International schools cost around €8,000/year (about 70,000 RMB).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are significant variations based on grade level, region, and school, with costs potentially differing by a factor of 1-2.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="-teaching-staff-and-pedagogical-features"&gt;🏫 Teaching Staff and Pedagogical Features&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Teacher absenteeism is relatively high in Spain. A doctor&amp;rsquo;s note for sick leave has legal standing and can be issued over the phone for paid sick leave.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Primary schools generally use a &amp;ldquo;generalist&amp;rdquo; system, where a single teacher teaches multiple subjects like English, math, humanities, science, art, and physical education, which may limit subject-specific expertise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subject-specific teaching only begins in secondary school.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The saying &amp;ldquo;the gym teacher taught my math&amp;rdquo; is not a joke in Spain but a result of the generalist system in primary schools.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exam scores are not ranked.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="-language-of-instruction-and-multilingual-environment"&gt;🈯 Language of Instruction and Multilingual Environment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;International schools primarily use English for instruction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Private and public schools mainly use Spanish.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Autonomous communities like Valencia and Catalonia require students to learn the local regional language.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In secondary school, a second foreign language such as French or German is added, making the multilingual workload demanding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="-workload-and-holiday-schedule"&gt;📖 Workload and Holiday Schedule&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is less homework.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The academic year is divided into three terms, with a total of about 160–180 teaching days.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Holidays are long.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="-comparison-with-basic-education-in-china"&gt;🇨🇳 Comparison with Basic Education in China&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Public Schools&lt;/strong&gt;: School hours are from 8:00 AM to 4:00 PM, with 6–8 classes per day. They are free, with some areas offering after-school care programs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Private/International Schools&lt;/strong&gt;: 8:00 AM to 5:30 PM, with evening self-study sessions starting in middle school, which do not exist in Spain.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Private: Approx. 60,000 RMB/year&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;International: Approx. 180,000 RMB/year&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The academic year is divided into two semesters, with over 190 teaching days.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="-disparity-in-campus-facilities"&gt;🏟️ Disparity in Campus Facilities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;International schools in China often boast campuses of over 100 acres, featuring heated swimming pools, theaters, multimedia libraries, maker labs, Olympic-standard stadiums, and even equestrian centers, golf courses, and drone and robotics labs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In contrast, Spanish schools are more modest and compact, with simpler facilities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="-curriculum-and-difficulty"&gt;📘 Curriculum and Difficulty&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people believe that primary school math in China is much harder than abroad, but this is a long-standing misconception.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>A Hiking Route in Chulilla, the Cliff Town: A 6km Journey Through a Millennium</title><link>/en/a-hiking-route-in-chulilla-the-cliff-town-a-6km-journey-through-a-millennium/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/a-hiking-route-in-chulilla-the-cliff-town-a-6km-journey-through-a-millennium/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;2025-01-28 23:52 Spain&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img loading="lazy" src="/images/wechat/adc4be0a4441.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ðStarting Point&lt;/strong&gt;: Town parking lot (39.6599279, -0.8916659)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;â±ï¸Duration&lt;/strong&gt;: 3 hours&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Valley Exploration&lt;/strong&gt;:
From the fork (39.6572005, -0.8921885), delve into the emerald river valley to reach the hidden Blue Lagoon (Charco Azul) (39.6650017, -0.8922144)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rope-Climbing to Caves + Hanging Bridges&lt;/strong&gt;,
Return to the fork via the bridges above the river.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Canyon Wonders&lt;/strong&gt;:
From the back mountain entrance (39.6572988, -0.8929979), loop around to the other side of the town (39.6546164, -0.8941087)&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>A Thousand-Year Turtle? When Will We Stop Taking Things for Granted?</title><link>/en/a-thousand-year-turtle-when-will-we-stop-taking-things-for-granted/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/a-thousand-year-turtle-when-will-we-stop-taking-things-for-granted/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Almost everyone has heard the old saying, &amp;ldquo;A turtle for a thousand years, a tortoise for ten thousand.&amp;rdquo; In Chinese culture, turtles and tortoises are seen as symbols of longevity, as if they are naturally destined to outlive several human generations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But here&amp;rsquo;s the question: &lt;strong&gt;Has there ever really been a turtle that lived for a thousand years?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people see a giant turtle or tortoise and exclaim, &amp;ldquo;Wow, this one must be hundreds of years old!&amp;rdquo; While such statements might &amp;ldquo;sound reasonable,&amp;rdquo; they actually &lt;strong&gt;don&amp;rsquo;t stand up to scrutiny&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>An Overview of European Ethnogenesis: A Long-Term Process of Migration, Language Replacement, and Institutional Integration</title><link>/en/an-overview-of-european-ethnogenesis-a-long-term-process-of-migration-language-replacement-and-institutional-integration/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/an-overview-of-european-ethnogenesis-a-long-term-process-of-migration-language-replacement-and-institutional-integration/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The ethnic structure of Europe is not fixed from antiquity but was gradually formed through a long historical process of &lt;strong&gt;prehistoric population migrations, language replacement, political conquest, and religious integration&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following sections outline the main stages and structural features of European ethnogenesis in &lt;strong&gt;chronological order&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id="i-neolithic-era-near-eastern-farmers-enter-europe"&gt;I. Neolithic Era: Near Eastern Farmers Enter Europe&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(c. 7000–5000 BCE)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source&lt;/strong&gt;
Near Eastern Fertile Crescent, Anatolia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Paternal Genetic Signature&lt;/strong&gt;
Represented by &lt;strong&gt;Haplogroup J (especially J2)&lt;/strong&gt; (not exclusively, but a significant proportion in the early agricultural diffusion)&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Ancient China: A Civilization That Once Left Europe Far Behind</title><link>/en/ancient-china-a-civilization-that-once-left-europe-far-behind/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/ancient-china-a-civilization-that-once-left-europe-far-behind/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;We are accustomed to thinking that &amp;ldquo;the West has always been ahead of China,&amp;rdquo; but this is actually a historical illusion shaped in reverse by the outcome of the Industrial Revolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="i-the-rear-view-mirror-illusion-of-history"&gt;I. The &amp;ldquo;Rear-View Mirror&amp;rdquo; Illusion of History&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, many Chinese people have an almost unconscious belief: &lt;strong&gt;the West seems inherently more advanced than China.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this is a typical historical illusion, &amp;ldquo;reverse-engineered&amp;rdquo; by the outcome of the Industrial Revolution.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Answering Philosophical Questions with Science: A Rational Reconstruction of Time, Meaning, Consciousness, Causality, and Morality</title><link>/en/answering-philosophical-questions-with-science-a-rational-reconstruction-of-time-meaning-consciousness-causality-and-morality/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/answering-philosophical-questions-with-science-a-rational-reconstruction-of-time-meaning-consciousness-causality-and-morality/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Throughout human history, a certain class of questions has been asked repeatedly for millennia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is time?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does life have meaning?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Must we fear death?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do we truly have free will?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where do good and evil come from?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These questions have long been categorized under &amp;ldquo;philosophy&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;metaphysics,&amp;rdquo; shrouded in layers of myth, religion, metaphor, and strong emotion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But today, with the advancements in physics, neuroscience, and information theory, we have the opportunity for the first time to—&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Does AI Have Memory?</title><link>/en/does-ai-have-memory/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/does-ai-have-memory/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;When many people use an AI chatbot for the first time, they might feel like it &amp;lsquo;remembers&amp;rsquo; what was said before. For example, if you ask a question and then follow up on it a little later, it can still connect the dots. This leads to a common question: Does AI actually have memory?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s start with the conclusion: An AI&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;memory&amp;rsquo; is not the file-based memory we imagine. It relies on predicting with parameter weights, not on hard-drive-style storage.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Essential Apps for Blue Zone Street Parking in Spain &amp; Money-Saving Tips for Long-Term Airport Parking</title><link>/en/essential-apps-for-blue-zone-street-parking-in-spain-money-saving-tips-for-long-term-airport-parking/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/essential-apps-for-blue-zone-street-parking-in-spain-money-saving-tips-for-long-term-airport-parking/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In Spain, commercial parking lots are generally expensive. A few hours can easily cost tens of euros, which is a significant expense. To save money, consider using free roadside parking spots or the paid blue zone parking spaces provided by the municipality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blue zone parking spaces are cheaper, costing around â¬1 per hour. However, paying manually can be a hassle. You need to go to a nearby payment machine, enter your license plate number and parking duration, and pay with coins or a card. If you leave early, the refund process is also quite complicated. Therefore, it&amp;rsquo;s highly recommended to use a convenient parking payment app for online payments and flexible billing, which is more economical and practical.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Europe Once 'Lost' an Entire Civilization: Why Did Ancient Greek Rational Knowledge Disappear in Medieval Europe?</title><link>/en/europe-once-lost-an-entire-civilization-why-did-ancient-greek-rational-knowledge-disappear-in-medieval-europe/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/europe-once-lost-an-entire-civilization-why-did-ancient-greek-rational-knowledge-disappear-in-medieval-europe/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Medieval Christian Europe experienced a systematic interruption of Greek mathematics, philosophy, and science due to linguistic fragmentation, the collapse of the educational system, and religious monopoly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast, Greek knowledge was fully preserved, translated, and developed in the Byzantine and Islamic worlds. It eventually returned to Europe through cross-civilizational transfer, igniting the Renaissance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people subconsciously assume that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since Europe is the successor to ancient Greece and Rome,
then mathematics, philosophy, and science
should have been passed down naturally through the ages.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>From Abraham's Family Drama to the Global 'One God'</title><link>/en/from-abraham-s-family-drama-to-the-global-one-god/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/from-abraham-s-family-drama-to-the-global-one-god/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="religion-a-4000-year-war-for-the-right-to-interpret"&gt;Religion: A 4,000-Year &amp;ldquo;War for the Right to Interpret&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the early days of human civilization, religion was like a chaotic &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;startup competition.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, our ancestors were timid:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They called the thunder &amp;lsquo;father&amp;rsquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They called the rain &amp;lsquo;mother&amp;rsquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And thus, the primitive worship of &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;animism&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; was born.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later on—&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ancient Egyptians deified their pets (jackals, cats)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ancient Greeks raised a group of &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;superpowered giant babies&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; on Mount Olympus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zeus and his family, instead of doing anything productive, spent their days cheating and bickering.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>From Emergence to Intelligence Phase Transition: How Large Language Models 'Sense' High-Dimensional Space</title><link>/en/from-emergence-to-intelligence-phase-transition-how-large-language-models-sense-high-dimensional-space/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/from-emergence-to-intelligence-phase-transition-how-large-language-models-sense-high-dimensional-space/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;When the massive parameters of a large language model intertwine into a web within the information space, the &amp;lsquo;intelligence&amp;rsquo; it exhibits is not a mysterious consciousness, but a natural product of emergence, self-organization, and high-dimensional information structures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And inspiration, perhaps, is merely the projection of a &lt;strong&gt;quantum fluctuation in a six-dimensional space&lt;/strong&gt; onto our four-dimensional spacetime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are always amazed by the &amp;lsquo;cleverness&amp;rsquo; of AI—&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It can write articles, reason, and code, sometimes even creating the illusion:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Get a SIP Card &amp; Vaccines in Spain Without Social Security: A Step-by-Step Guide</title><link>/en/get-a-sip-card-vaccines-in-spain-without-social-security-a-step-by-step-guide/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/get-a-sip-card-vaccines-in-spain-without-social-security-a-step-by-step-guide/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I recently went through the process myself at the local health center (Centre de Salut L’Eliana) in &lt;strong&gt;L’Eliana&lt;/strong&gt;, in the Valencian Community, and discovered that &lt;strong&gt;even foreigners without social security contributions can get a free SIP card and receive flu and COVID-19 mRNA vaccines!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, I&amp;rsquo;m sharing the detailed process to help anyone who might need it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id="-what-is-a-sip-card"&gt;💡 What is a SIP card?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SIP is the personal identification card for the Spanish healthcare system. The full name is &lt;strong&gt;“Sistema de Información Poblacional”&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Hiking Route Recommendation: Garbi</title><link>/en/hiking-route-recommendation-garbi/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/hiking-route-recommendation-garbi/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Please provide the body of the article that needs to be optimized, and I will format it in Markdown according to your requirements.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>How to Apply for a Spanish Fishing License Online</title><link>/en/how-to-apply-for-a-spanish-fishing-license-online/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/how-to-apply-for-a-spanish-fishing-license-online/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In Spain, fishing licenses are mainly divided into two categories: &lt;strong&gt;sea fishing licenses&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;river (freshwater) fishing licenses&lt;/strong&gt;. This article will provide a detailed guide on how to apply for both types of licenses online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id="i-sea-fishing-license-application-process"&gt;I. Sea Fishing License Application Process&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The application process for sea fishing licenses is relatively uniform across different regions of Spain. You can apply directly online through the official website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="-official-website-for-sea-fishing-licenses"&gt;🔗 Official Website for Sea Fishing Licenses&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Application URL:
&lt;a href="https://www.gva.es/es/inicio/procedimientos?id_proc=647&amp;amp;id_caso=sollicitud#presentacion"&gt;https://www.gva.es/es/inicio/procedimientos?id_proc=647&amp;id_caso=sollicitud#presentacion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>How to Apply Online for a ''Collective Address Certificate'' for a Minor</title><link>/en/how-to-apply-online-for-a-collective-address-certificate-for-a-minor/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/how-to-apply-online-for-a-collective-address-certificate-for-a-minor/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In Spain, the address certificate (empadronamiento) is one of the most commonly used official documents, widely used for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A minor&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong&gt;residency renewal (renovación del menor)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;School registration / transfer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Health card (SIP) application&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Applications for family subsidies, childcare benefits, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a child is involved, the standard requirement is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Certificado de empadronamiento colectivo (Collective Address Certificate)&lt;/strong&gt;
This document proves that the child lives with their parents/guardians and is the only valid document recognized by all government departments.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>How to Self-Study Efficiently and Quickly Pass the Spanish B Driving License Theory Test</title><link>/en/how-to-self-study-efficiently-and-quickly-pass-the-spanish-b-driving-license-theory-test/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/how-to-self-study-efficiently-and-quickly-pass-the-spanish-b-driving-license-theory-test/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="1-how-to-study-for-the-theory-test"&gt;1. How to Study for the Theory Test&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is highly recommended not to just cram questions, because:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The question bank is vast. The English version has over 200 sets of tests, each with 30 questions, totaling more than 6,000 questions. Completing them all is time-consuming and exhausting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The translations and questions in the bank may not be accurate, and the answers could be wrong.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The actual exam questions are not taken directly from the question bank, so finishing it is not a guarantee.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The knowledge in the question bank is fragmented and not systematic. Without systematic learning, you might not be able to answer if a question is phrased differently.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Efficient Learning Method:&lt;/strong&gt; Since I took the English exam, the following content is based on English materials.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>If I 'Die' Every Day, Does My Life Still Have Meaning?</title><link>/en/if-i-die-every-day-does-my-life-still-have-meaning/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/if-i-die-every-day-does-my-life-still-have-meaning/</guid><description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introduction:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If one day you discover that &amp;ldquo;you&amp;rdquo; can be perfectly replicated, does your current existence still have meaning?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the logic and reasoning of AI gradually approach or even surpass that of humans, we may have to confront a cruel yet rational fact: consciousness might not be a soul, but rather a &amp;ldquo;model&amp;rdquo; that is currently running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id="i-defining-consciousness-the-ultimatum-from-ai"&gt;I. Defining Consciousness: The &amp;ldquo;Ultimatum&amp;rdquo; from AI&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before discussing &amp;ldquo;who I am,&amp;rdquo; we must first let go of the sanctified image of the self.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Is Sending Kids to Study in the West Really Better for Their Mental Health?</title><link>/en/is-sending-kids-to-study-in-the-west-really-better-for-their-mental-health/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/is-sending-kids-to-study-in-the-west-really-better-for-their-mental-health/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Many parents send their children to study in Europe or the US for a common reason:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Education abroad is more relaxed, so kids have less stress, are less prone to depression, and it&amp;rsquo;s better for their mental health.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It sounds reasonable: children in China have a lot of homework, fierce competition, and frequent exams, while children abroad seem happier, getting out of school around 3 PM for sports, clubs, dances, and summer camps.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Learning Spanish Made Me Realize Why Chinese is the Most "Scientific" Language</title><link>/en/learning-spanish-made-me-realize-why-chinese-is-the-most-scientific-language/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/learning-spanish-made-me-realize-why-chinese-is-the-most-scientific-language/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;No verb conjugations, no grammatical gender, and highly efficient and precise expression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The logical beauty of Chinese is not just something to marvel at, but something to be confident about.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id="-theres-a-confidence-we-should-express-loudly"&gt;🇨🇳 There&amp;rsquo;s a Confidence We Should Express Loudly&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Living abroad these past two years, I&amp;rsquo;ve often heard some Chinese friends &lt;strong&gt;belittle their own mother tongue and culture&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Chinese people aren&amp;rsquo;t as beautiful as white people.&amp;rdquo;
&amp;ldquo;Chinese people have always been uncivilized.&amp;rdquo;
&amp;ldquo;The Chinese diet is too eclectic.&amp;rdquo;
&amp;ldquo;Our language lacks class; it&amp;rsquo;s not as high-end as English.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>My Experience Passing the Spanish Driving Road Test</title><link>/en/my-experience-passing-the-spanish-driving-road-test/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/my-experience-passing-the-spanish-driving-road-test/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I passed my road test, and I&amp;rsquo;m here to share my experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the driving road test in Spain, the examiner will only give instructions in Spanish, and the instructor is generally not allowed to translate. Therefore, it is crucial to master the following common Spanish commands and their expressions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Start the engine&lt;/strong&gt;: Arrancar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Turn right&lt;/strong&gt;: Derecha&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Turn left&lt;/strong&gt;: Izquierda&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Go straight&lt;/strong&gt;: Recto&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make a U-turn&lt;/strong&gt;: Cambio de sentido&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Indirect left turn&lt;/strong&gt;: izquierda indirecto&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Roundabout&lt;/strong&gt;: Rotonda&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First exit&lt;/strong&gt;: Primera salida&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Second exit&lt;/strong&gt;: Segunda salida&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Third exit&lt;/strong&gt;: Tercera salida&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fourth exit&lt;/strong&gt;: Cuarta salida&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stop&lt;/strong&gt;: Parar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Park&lt;/strong&gt;: Aparcar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don&amp;rsquo;t hear an instruction clearly, you can ask the examiner to repeat it in Spanish, for example: &amp;ldquo;Por favor repita&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Northern Spain Summer Road Trip: From Valencia to Covadonga</title><link>/en/northern-spain-summer-road-trip-from-valencia-to-covadonga/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/northern-spain-summer-road-trip-from-valencia-to-covadonga/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Last summer, I completed a 10-day grand road trip loop through northern Spain. &lt;strong&gt;Starting from Valencia, we traveled through Zaragoza, Olite, Bilbao, Santander, Comillas, Covadonga, Salamanca, Ávila, and Madrid, finally returning to Valencia after lunch in the cliff town of Cuenca.&lt;/strong&gt; This journey offered a mix of cities, ancient castles, mountains, the sea, and delicious food. This article shares all the details of our trip for four people, serving as a direct reference for anyone interested.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Same Symptoms, Different Causes—Don't Let Intuition Delay Your Treatment</title><link>/en/same-symptoms-different-causes-don-t-let-intuition-delay-your-treatment/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/same-symptoms-different-causes-don-t-let-intuition-delay-your-treatment/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;We often say, &amp;ldquo;If you&amp;rsquo;re sick, get treated promptly.&amp;rdquo; But often, the real problem isn&amp;rsquo;t about being &amp;ldquo;prompt&amp;rdquo; but about being:
&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Treated correctly.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When faced with discomfort, many people&amp;rsquo;s first reaction is to judge based on experience:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;🧠 &amp;ldquo;Nasal congestion? Must be rhinitis.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;🧠 &amp;ldquo;A cough? Just a cold.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;🧠 &amp;ldquo;A headache? I&amp;rsquo;ll just take a painkiller.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then they begin to self-diagnose and self-medicate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the truth is, &lt;strong&gt;many different illnesses can present with the exact same symptoms.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Spanish Local Income Analysis (Madrid vs. Beijing: Who Can Live a More Decent Life?)</title><link>/en/spanish-local-income-analysis-madrid-vs-beijing-who-can-live-a-more-decent-life/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/spanish-local-income-analysis-madrid-vs-beijing-who-can-live-a-more-decent-life/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;My previous article, [《The Downsides of Living in Spain: A Detailed 2024 Comparison of Madrid vs. Beijing》], sparked considerable debate despite objectively presenting Spain&amp;rsquo;s cost of living with reliable data. One commenter asked, &amp;ldquo;Why not compare the income of Spanish locals? For them, these prices are nothing.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, let&amp;rsquo;s complete the picture today: &lt;strong&gt;What are the income levels in Madrid and Beijing really like? We&amp;rsquo;ll cover high-income earners, blue-collar workers, and post-tax disposable income all in one go.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Spanish Non-Lucrative Visa Renewal Online (EX01): A Complete Guide for a Family of Three (Including a Minor)</title><link>/en/spanish-non-lucrative-visa-renewal-online-ex01-a-complete-guide-for-a-family-of-three-including-a-minor/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/spanish-non-lucrative-visa-renewal-online-ex01-a-complete-guide-for-a-family-of-three-including-a-minor/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="1-submission-time-requirements"&gt;1. Submission Time Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: left"&gt;Item&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: left"&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Earliest Submission Time&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;60 days&lt;/strong&gt; before NIE expiration&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Latest Submission Time&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Within &lt;strong&gt;90 days&lt;/strong&gt; after NIE expiration&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h3 id="financial-requirements-explained"&gt;Financial Requirements Explained&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The non-lucrative visa renewal is for a &lt;strong&gt;2-year period&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One year requires &lt;strong&gt;4 times the IPREM&lt;/strong&gt;, so two years require &lt;strong&gt;8 times&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For each additional family member, add &lt;strong&gt;1 time the IPREM&lt;/strong&gt; for one year, and &lt;strong&gt;2 times&lt;/strong&gt; for two years.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, using the official 2025 figures:
&lt;strong&gt;IPREM = €7,200 / year&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Distance from Beijing to Shanghai: Understanding LLM Text Embeddings and RAG with Vector Databases</title><link>/en/the-distance-from-beijing-to-shanghai-understanding-llm-text-embeddings-and-rag-with-vector-databases/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/the-distance-from-beijing-to-shanghai-understanding-llm-text-embeddings-and-rag-with-vector-databases/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;We often say, &amp;ldquo;Large Language Models are very smart.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They can write articles, answer questions, code, and even perform some logical reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in reality, the principle behind them isn&amp;rsquo;t mysterious:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;👉 It just turns a piece of text into a string of numbers,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;👉 and then &amp;ldquo;calculates the distance&amp;rdquo; in a high-dimensional space.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This might sound a bit abstract, but with a small example, you&amp;rsquo;ll understand it right away. 👇&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Downsides of Living in Spain: A Detailed 2024 Comparison of Madrid vs. Beijing</title><link>/en/the-downsides-of-living-in-spain-a-detailed-2024-comparison-of-madrid-vs-beijing/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/the-downsides-of-living-in-spain-a-detailed-2024-comparison-of-madrid-vs-beijing/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Spain has long been regarded as a country with a high quality of life in Europe, attracting a large number of immigrants and international students. However, when we make a direct comparison with China, especially its capital Beijing, we find that Spain has significant shortcomings in many core aspects of life. Based on the latest data from 2024, this article provides a systematic comparison between Madrid and Beijing across dimensions such as consumer costs, education, healthcare, transportation, housing, home appliances, cars, and public safety, deeply revealing the various inconveniences and cost pressures of life in Spain.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Nature of the Han People: 5,000 Years of Huaxia Bloodline and Chinese Culture</title><link>/en/the-nature-of-the-han-people-5-000-years-of-huaxia-bloodline-and-chinese-culture/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/the-nature-of-the-han-people-5-000-years-of-huaxia-bloodline-and-chinese-culture/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="1-mythical-beginnings-yan-huang-and-chiyou"&gt;1. Mythical Beginnings: Yan, Huang, and Chiyou&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As recorded in the &lt;em&gt;Records of the Grand Historian&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Discourses of the States&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Yellow Emperor (Huangdi) defeated the Yan Emperor (Yandi) at the Battle of Banquan, causing the Yan tribe to submit to his rule.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He then defeated Chiyou at the Battle of Zhuolu, achieving ultimate victory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are not merely legends but symbols of the integration of ancient tribes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Yellow Emperor&amp;rsquo;s group&lt;/strong&gt;: An agricultural tribe from the Central Plains, with the surname Ji.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Yan Emperor&amp;rsquo;s group&lt;/strong&gt;: A tribe with the surname Jiang, related to the ancient Qiang people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chiyou&amp;rsquo;s group&lt;/strong&gt;: The Jiuli (Nine Li) tribes, ancestors of the Miao-Man peoples of the south.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, the people of the Yan Emperor and Chiyou were incorporated into the Yellow Emperor&amp;rsquo;s tribe, forming the &amp;ldquo;Huaxia.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Pinnacle of Algorithms and the Source of Logic: When the Nine Chapters on the Mathematical Art Meets Euclid's Elements</title><link>/en/the-pinnacle-of-algorithms-and-the-source-of-logic-when-the-nine-chapters-on-the-mathematical-art-meets-euclid-s-elements/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/the-pinnacle-of-algorithms-and-the-source-of-logic-when-the-nine-chapters-on-the-mathematical-art-meets-euclid-s-elements/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;At the dawn of human civilization, two mathematical works emerged in almost the same era. Like two rivers flowing in different directions, they quietly shaped the &lt;strong&gt;completely different intellectual traditions&lt;/strong&gt; of the East and West.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One came from China,
the other from ancient Greece.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;China&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nine Chapters on the Mathematical Art&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ancient Greece&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Elements&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (from Euclid&amp;rsquo;s work)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To this day, our understanding of &lt;strong&gt;science, technology, and even artificial intelligence&lt;/strong&gt; still carries the DNA of these two books.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Truth About Europe's Royal Families: They Were Almost All German</title><link>/en/the-truth-about-europe-s-royal-families-they-were-almost-all-german/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/the-truth-about-europe-s-royal-families-they-were-almost-all-german/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Many people assume that,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The British royal family is British,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The French royal family is French,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the Spanish royal family is, naturally, Spanish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if you take even a brief look at the history of European royalty, you&amp;rsquo;ll discover a fact that seems absurd, yet is entirely true—&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The core of the entire European royal system is almost entirely of German origin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And not just a little bit. We&amp;rsquo;re talking about a systemic presence.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Was the Imperial Examination in Ancient China Only About the Eight-Legged Essay? (The Earliest Version Balanced Arts and Sciences)</title><link>/en/was-the-imperial-examination-in-ancient-china-only-about-the-eight-legged-essay-the-earliest-version-balanced-arts-and-sciences/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/was-the-imperial-examination-in-ancient-china-only-about-the-eight-legged-essay-the-earliest-version-balanced-arts-and-sciences/</guid><description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Historical and archaeological clarification:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The imperial examination system was not solely about the eight-legged essay; it originally promoted a balance of arts and sciences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The foundation of Han civilization&amp;rsquo;s belief system is rationality and ethics, not theocracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Europe was consumed by faith, China had long esteemed science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id="many-people-assume-that-the-ancient-imperial-examinations-only-tested-on-the-eight-legged-essay-and-that-scholars-were-all-bookworms"&gt;Many people assume that the ancient imperial examinations only tested on the eight-legged essay, and that scholars were all &amp;ldquo;bookworms.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the opposite is true.
For a very long time, the true imperial examination system was a balance of arts and sciences.
Ancient China was not just a land of poetry, books, rites, and music; it was a civilization that revered science and reason.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Why Did Europe Turn to Democracy? — The Republican Tradition, Not an Accidental Historical Choice</title><link>/en/why-did-europe-turn-to-democracy-the-republican-tradition-not-an-accidental-historical-choice/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/why-did-europe-turn-to-democracy-the-republican-tradition-not-an-accidental-historical-choice/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;When people talk about European democracy, they often focus on a specific revolution or declaration, as if democracy were an institutional innovation that suddenly appeared one day in modern times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if we look back through history, we discover a more fundamental and often overlooked fact:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Europe did not suddenly learn republicanism;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;it has long lived with the political experience that &amp;lsquo;a republic can exist.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The republic in Europe was never a fleeting moment of inspiration,
but an institutional tradition spanning over two millennia.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>