<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>trigger on zixia</title><link>/en/trigger/</link><description>Recent content in trigger on zixia</description><generator>Hugo -- 0.155.0</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/en/trigger/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>```json</title><link>/en/song-hai-zi-qu-ou-mei-liu-xue-zhen-de-geng-li-yu-xin-li-jian-kang-ma/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/song-hai-zi-qu-ou-mei-liu-xue-zhen-de-geng-li-yu-xin-li-jian-kang-ma/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;{
&amp;ldquo;title&amp;rdquo;: &amp;ldquo;Is Sending Kids to Study in the West Really Better for Their Mental Health?&amp;rdquo;,
&amp;ldquo;body&amp;rdquo;: &amp;ldquo;Many parents send their children to study in Europe or the US for a common reason:\n\n&amp;gt; &amp;quot;Education abroad is more relaxed, so kids have less stress, are less prone to depression, and it&amp;rsquo;s better for their mental health.&amp;quot;\n\nIt sounds reasonable: children in China have a lot of homework, fierce competition, and frequent exams, while children abroad seem happier, getting out of school around 3 PM for sports, clubs, dances, and summer camps.\n\nBut is this really the case? I had an in-depth discussion with an AI using data, and the conclusion might upend your assumptions.\n\n&amp;mdash;\n\n## 01 Starting with the Intuition that &amp;quot;Stress = Mental Health Problems&amp;quot;\n\nInitially, the AI&amp;rsquo;s response was like most people&amp;rsquo;s:\n\n&amp;gt; &amp;quot;American education is more relaxed and thus more beneficial for adolescent mental health.&amp;quot;\n\nThe reasoning was: less stress → less anxiety → better mental health.\n\nThis sounds logical, but it&amp;rsquo;s based on impressions and speculation, not data.\n\nSo I pressed further: &amp;quot;Can we compare this using quantitative metrics, like depression rates or suicide rates?&amp;quot;\n\n&amp;mdash;\n\n## 02 Depression Rates: A Wide Discrepancy in Data\n\nThe AI found data on adolescent depression rates in China and the US, revealing a huge statistical variance for China:\n\n| Metric | China | United States |\n| &amp;mdash; | &amp;mdash; | &amp;mdash; |\n| &lt;strong&gt;Diagnosed Depressive Disorder&lt;/strong&gt; | ≈ &lt;strong&gt;2%&lt;/strong&gt; (6–16 years, national review, Child &amp;amp; Adolescent Psychiatry &amp;amp; Mental Health 2024) | ≈ &lt;strong&gt;19–20%&lt;/strong&gt; (12–17 years, major depressive episode in the past year, NIMH / SAMHSA NSDUH 2021–2022) |\n| &lt;strong&gt;Symptom Screening (Blue Book)&lt;/strong&gt; | 14.8% (2022 edition), 24.6% (2020 edition) | – |\n| &lt;strong&gt;Meta-analysis Summary&lt;/strong&gt; | ≈ 26% (synthesis of 439 studies) | – |\n| &lt;strong&gt;Large-sample CES-D Study&lt;/strong&gt; | 39.93% positive | – |\n| &lt;strong&gt;PHQ-9 Positive (last 2 weeks)&lt;/strong&gt; | – | 19.2% (CDC NHANES 2021–2023) |\n| &lt;strong&gt;Self-reported sadness/hopelessness in school&lt;/strong&gt; | – | 42% (CDC YRBS 2021) |\n\nLooking only at this data, it&amp;rsquo;s easy to conclude that depression among Chinese adolescents is severe. However, depressive symptoms are heavily influenced by screening thresholds and cultural expression, so they can&amp;rsquo;t be the sole standard.\n\n&amp;mdash;\n\n## 03 Suicide Rates: The Most Objective Mental Health Indicator\n\nTo eliminate cultural and measurement biases, I looked up adolescent suicide rates. The results were very clear:\n\n| Country | Age Group | Year | Suicide Rate (per 100,000) | Source |\n| &amp;mdash; | &amp;mdash; | &amp;mdash; | &amp;mdash; | &amp;mdash; |\n| China | 10–19 years | 2021 | &lt;strong&gt;2.83&lt;/strong&gt; | JAMA Pediatrics 2023 |\n| United States | 10–24 years | 2021 | &lt;strong&gt;11.0&lt;/strong&gt; | CDC NCHS Data Brief 471 |\n\nThe adolescent suicide rate in the US is 3-4 times that of China. Even accounting for differences in statistical scope, the US rate is still significantly higher.\n\n
&lt;img loading="lazy" src="/images/wechat/95e9a1fd9820.png"&gt;
\n\n&amp;mdash;\n\n## 04 The AI Admits Its &amp;quot;Mistake&amp;quot;\n\nWhen I presented this data to the AI, it frankly admitted:\n\n&amp;gt; &amp;quot;My previous conclusion was based more on assumptions from my training data and general public opinion—that &amp;lsquo;high stress = poor mental health&amp;rsquo;—rather than reasoning from hard data.&amp;quot;\n\nIt also stated that in the future, it would &lt;strong&gt;base its reasoning on objective data&lt;/strong&gt; to avoid preconceived judgments and be truly scientific, objective, and fair.\n\nThis conversation left a deep impression on me: many parents, teachers, and even experts often rely on intuition rather than evidence when discussing &amp;quot;mental health.&amp;quot; The facts and public opinion can be two different things.\n\n
&lt;img loading="lazy" src="/images/wechat/efafb2ab495f.png"&gt;
\n\n&amp;mdash;\n\n## 05 The Rebound During the Pandemic\n\nIt&amp;rsquo;s worth noting that after hitting a low of &lt;strong&gt;1.59 per 100,000&lt;/strong&gt; in 2017, China&amp;rsquo;s adolescent suicide rate &lt;strong&gt;rebounded to 2.83 per 100,000&lt;/strong&gt; in 2021.\n\nThis period coincided with the online learning phase of the COVID-19 pandemic. Many children were at home for online classes, lacking a classroom atmosphere, losing motivation to study, becoming addicted to online games and short videos, having their routines disrupted, and even experiencing increased conflict with family. Their mental state fluctuated.\n\nFrom this perspective, this rebound precisely illustrates that—\n\n&lt;strong&gt;Focused study and a regular lifestyle are important protective factors for adolescent mental health.&lt;/strong&gt;\n\nWhen the rhythm of learning was disrupted and children were just &amp;quot;going through the motions&amp;quot; by playing games on their computers, their mental health actually worsened.\n\n&amp;mdash;\n\n## 06 Stress Might Be Training for Psychological Resilience\n\nThe data tells us something unexpected:\n\n&amp;gt; Academic pressure does not necessarily lead to mental collapse; on the contrary, it may cultivate a child&amp;rsquo;s resilience.\n\nChinese children have to deal with exams, rankings, and comparisons from a young age, which teaches them emotional regulation and how to cope with setbacks earlier. In contrast, an overly relaxed environment may not help children deal with real-world pressures, potentially making them more fragile when they encounter genuine difficulties.\n\n&amp;mdash;\n\n## 07 Takeaways for Parents\n\n* &lt;strong&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t panic about pressure&lt;/strong&gt;: Moderate academic stress can cultivate a sense of purpose and resilience.\n* &lt;strong&gt;Mental health isn&amp;rsquo;t just about &amp;quot;having fun&amp;quot;&lt;/strong&gt;: A regular routine, engagement in learning, and family support are more crucial.\n* &lt;strong&gt;Studying abroad is not a panacea&lt;/strong&gt;: Adolescent suicide rates are higher in the West. Don&amp;rsquo;t see studying abroad as the only solution to mental health problems.\n\n&amp;mdash;\n\n## 08 Conclusion\n\nJudging by the hard metric of suicide rates, the mental health of Chinese adolescents is no worse than that of their American counterparts, and may even be better.\n\nThe rebound during the pandemic also reminds us:\n\n&amp;gt; &lt;strong&gt;Maintaining a regular study routine and focus is an important safeguard for mental health, not indulging in online games.&lt;/strong&gt;\n\nAnd the AI in this discussion also gave us a reminder:\n\n&amp;gt; &lt;strong&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t blindly follow &amp;quot;public opinion and impressions.&amp;quot; Instead, use objective data to reason and arrive at more truthful conclusions.&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo;
}&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>```json</title><link>/en/zai-xi-ban-ya-mei-jiao-she-bao-ye-neng-ban-sip-ka-she-bao-ka-da-yi-miao-qin-shen-shi-lu-fen-xiang/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/zai-xi-ban-ya-mei-jiao-she-bao-ye-neng-ban-sip-ka-she-bao-ka-da-yi-miao-qin-shen-shi-lu-fen-xiang/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;{
&amp;ldquo;title&amp;rdquo;: &amp;ldquo;Get a SIP Card and Vaccinations in Spain Without Social Security: A Step-by-Step Guide&amp;rdquo;,
&amp;ldquo;body&amp;rdquo;: &amp;ldquo;I recently went through the process myself at the community health center (Centre de Salut L’Eliana) in &lt;strong&gt;L’Eliana&lt;/strong&gt;, in the Valencian Community, and discovered that &lt;strong&gt;even foreigners without social security contributions can get a free SIP card and receive flu and COVID-19 mRNA vaccines!&lt;/strong&gt;\n\nToday, I&amp;rsquo;m sharing the entire process in detail to help anyone who might need it.\n\n&amp;mdash;\n\n### 💡 What is a SIP card?\n\nSIP is the personal identification card for the Spanish healthcare system. The full name is &lt;strong&gt;“Sistema de Información Poblacional”&lt;/strong&gt;.\n\nWith this card, you can:\n\n* Visit public hospitals or community health centers;\n* Receive various vaccines provided by the state (including flu, COVID-19, etc.);\n* Get discounts on prescription medications;\n* Keep a record of your vaccinations and medical history.\n\n
&lt;img loading="lazy" src="/images/wechat/925f956c0bae.jpg"&gt;
\n\n&amp;mdash;\n\n### 🪪 1. What kind of SIP card can you get without social security?\n\nFor foreigners who are not working and not contributing to social security (such as those on non-lucrative visas, students, parents accompanying students, etc.), you can apply for a temporary SIP card &lt;strong&gt;“without healthcare coverage (sin cobertura sanitaria)”&lt;/strong&gt;.\n\nThis type of SIP card will be marked with “&lt;strong&gt;PRIVAD&lt;/strong&gt;”, which means you are temporarily not entitled to national health insurance reimbursement, but it &lt;strong&gt;can be used for vaccinations and emergency medical services&lt;/strong&gt;.\n\n📍My card says:\n\n&amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;Sin cobertura sanitaria – Pública gratuita vacunación y urgencias&lt;/em&gt;\n&amp;gt; (Without healthcare coverage, free vaccination and emergency services)\n\nThis type of SIP card is &lt;strong&gt;permanently valid&lt;/strong&gt;; as long as your information doesn&amp;rsquo;t change, you don&amp;rsquo;t need to renew it annually.\n\n&amp;mdash;\n\n### 📍 2. Where to apply?\n\nGo directly to the &lt;strong&gt;Centro de Salud (community health center)&lt;/strong&gt; in your residential area.\n\nFor example, in my town:\n\n&amp;gt; &lt;strong&gt;Centre de Salut L’Eliana&lt;/strong&gt;\n&amp;gt; Address: Av. del Parc, 3\n&amp;gt; Office Hours: Monday to Friday 8:00–20:00\n&amp;gt; (SIP Application Hours: Monday to Friday 9:45–13:30)\n\nThe red sign at the entrance clearly states👇\n\n&amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;Conselleria de Sanitat Universal i Salut Pública&lt;/em&gt;\n&amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;Generalitat Valenciana&lt;/em&gt;\n\n&amp;mdash;\n\n
&lt;img loading="lazy" src="/images/wechat/f921d4260064.png"&gt;
\n\n### 🧾 3. Required Documents\n\nThe staff only required the following three items:\n\n1. ✅ Passport or NIE (residence card)\n2. ✅ Proof of address (empadronamiento, also known as padrón)\n3. ✅ Phone number, email address\n\nNo social security number or private health insurance is needed.\n\nAs long as you are a resident in the area, you can register and get a SIP number.\n\n&amp;mdash;\n\n### 🪙 4. Application Process\n\n1️⃣ Go to the front desk of the health center and say:\n\n&amp;gt; “Hola, quiero solicitar una tarjeta SIP.”\n&amp;gt; (Hello, I would like to apply for a SIP card.)\n\n2️⃣ The staff will check your ID and address information.\n\n3️⃣ After a few minutes, they will print out a temporary paper SIP card on the spot (white paper with red text).\n\n4️⃣ If you have a residence card or long-term residency proof, you can apply for a formal plastic card.\n\nThe whole process was very fast; I got mine in about 10 minutes.\n\n
&lt;img loading="lazy" src="/images/wechat/5e2b7583d416.png"&gt;
\n\n&amp;mdash;\n\n### 💉 5. Vaccination Process (Flu + COVID)\n\nIn the Valencian Community, a unified &lt;strong&gt;“Flu + COVID-19 Vaccination Campaign”&lt;/strong&gt; starts in mid-October every year.\n\nThis year&amp;rsquo;s (2025) poster says:\n\n&amp;gt; 🗓 &lt;strong&gt;Dates: October 16 to November 30&lt;/strong&gt;\n&amp;gt; 🕒 Monday, Thursday, Friday 10:00–13:00\n&amp;gt; 🕓 Specific dates in the afternoon 15:00–18:00\n&amp;gt; 📍 Location: Centre de Formación de Personas Adultas, L’Eliana (Av. del Parque, 3)\n\nThe key point is—\n\n&amp;gt; &lt;strong&gt;No requiere cita previa (No appointment needed)&lt;/strong&gt;\n&amp;gt; Just bring your &lt;strong&gt;SIP card&lt;/strong&gt;!\n\nThe atmosphere on-site was very relaxed. Volunteers and nurses will help you register and get vaccinated.\n\nOne flu shot, one COVID shot, all done in a few minutes.\n\nSeniors, patients with chronic illnesses, children, and foreign residents can all get vaccinated for free.\n\n&amp;mdash;\n\n### 🧍‍♀️ 6. On-site Experience\n\nThe vaccination site was set up at the municipal adult education center. The queue wasn&amp;rsquo;t long, about a 20-minute wait, mostly with elderly people.\n\nThe nurses were very skilled.\n\n
&lt;img loading="lazy" src="/images/wechat/76a33f55aea8.png"&gt;
\n\n💬 A nurse on-site specifically emphasized:\n\n&amp;gt; “As long as you have a SIP card, you can get vaccinated, regardless of whether you contribute to social security.”\n\n&amp;mdash;\n\n### 💬 7. Frequently Asked Questions (Q&amp;amp;A)\n\n&lt;strong&gt;Q1: My SIP card says “PRIVAD”. Can I get vaccinated?&lt;/strong&gt;\n✅ Yes! This type of card specifically allows for free vaccinations.\n\n&lt;strong&gt;Q2: Does the temporary SIP card have an expiration date?&lt;/strong&gt;\n⏳ It doesn&amp;rsquo;t have a fixed expiration date. As long as your information remains the same, it stays valid.\n\n&lt;strong&gt;Q3: Can I apply without a padrón (address registration)?&lt;/strong&gt;\n❌ No. The padrón is the only proof that you live in the area, and it is mandatory. If you have a personal digital certificate, you can apply for and print it for free directly from the city hall&amp;rsquo;s website of your registered area, saving you a trip. For minors, parents can use their digital certificate to apply on their behalf under the collective residence certificate section on the city hall&amp;rsquo;s website. Approval takes about 1-3 business days, after which you can download the PDF certificate, all for free.\n\n&lt;strong&gt;Q4: Can I bring my child to get vaccinated?&lt;/strong&gt;\n👧 Yes, children can also get their own SIP card. You just need to bring their NIE and padrón certificate; the child does not need to be present.\n\n&amp;mdash;\n\n### ❤️ 8. Conclusion\n\nIn Spain, even if you don&amp;rsquo;t have a job or contribute to social security, as long as you are a resident, you can access &lt;strong&gt;basic public health services&lt;/strong&gt;.\n\nSo don&amp;rsquo;t hesitate—grab your passport and proof of address, and go to your local health center to get a SIP card!\n\nNot only will you be able to get vaccinated, but it also creates a convenient record for future medical care.\n\n&amp;mdash;\n\n📌 &lt;strong&gt;Summary of Practical Information:&lt;/strong&gt;\n\n| Item | Information |\n| &amp;mdash; | &amp;mdash; |\n| Where to Apply | Centre de Salut (Community Health Center) |\n| Required Documents | Passport/NIE + Padrón (proof of address) |\n| Social Security Required? | ❌ No |\n| Appointment Required? | ❌ No |\n| Available Vaccines | Flu / COVID-19 / Childhood vaccines, etc. |\n| Cost | Free |\n| Eligible Population | All residents in Spain (including foreigners) |\n\n&amp;mdash;&amp;rdquo;
}&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>```json</title><link>/en/xi-ban-ya-jie-dao-lan-xian-ting-che-bi-bei-app-ji-ji-chang-zhang-shi-ting-che-sheng-qian-gong-lve/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/xi-ban-ya-jie-dao-lan-xian-ting-che-bi-bei-app-ji-ji-chang-zhang-shi-ting-che-sheng-qian-gong-lve/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;{
&amp;ldquo;title&amp;rdquo;: &amp;ldquo;Essential Apps for Blue Zone Street Parking in Spain &amp;amp; Money-Saving Tips for Long-Term Airport Parking&amp;rdquo;,
&amp;ldquo;body&amp;rdquo;: &amp;ldquo;In Spain, commercial parking lots are generally expensive. A few hours can cost tens of euros, which is a significant expense. To save money, consider using free street parking spots or the paid blue zone parking spaces provided by the municipality.\n\nBlue zone parking spaces are cheaper, costing around €1 per hour. However, manual payment is cumbersome. You need to go to a nearby payment machine, enter your license plate number and parking duration, and pay with coins or a card. If you leave early, the refund process is also quite complicated. Therefore, it&amp;rsquo;s highly recommended to use a convenient parking payment app for online payments and flexible billing, which is more economical and practical.\n\nAdditionally, taxi fares to Spanish airports are high. Traveling from a smaller city to Madrid airport by train or bus can be troublesome and time-consuming. It&amp;rsquo;s much more convenient if you can park your own car near the airport and drive home directly upon your return. However, official airport parking is expensive, and long-term parking fees can be a major expense. So, how can you save money? In fact, there are specialized long-term parking lots near Spanish airports, with costs around €4 per day. This option is the most cost-effective, especially when traveling in a group.\n\n## 1. Essential Apps for Blue Zone Street Parking in Spain: Telpark &amp;amp; EasyPark\n\n### Telpark: The Top Choice for Local Residents\n\nTelpark is a widely used roadside parking payment app in Spain, covering blue zone parking spaces in most cities across the country and numerous public car parks.\n\n&lt;strong&gt;Telpark&amp;rsquo;s Key Features:&lt;/strong&gt;\n\n* &lt;strong&gt;Mobile Payment&lt;/strong&gt;: No cash needed, pay online anytime, anywhere.\n* &lt;strong&gt;Remote Renewal Reminders&lt;/strong&gt;: Get automatic reminders before your parking expires, allowing you to extend your time and avoid fines.\n* &lt;strong&gt;Parking Location Log&lt;/strong&gt;: Automatically saves your parking spot, making it easy to find your car.\n* &lt;strong&gt;Easy Bill Management&lt;/strong&gt;: View and download your parking invoices at any time.\n\n&lt;strong&gt;Best for&lt;/strong&gt;: Daily city commuters.\n\nMunicipal parking spaces usually have a maximum stay of 2 hours. If you need to park for longer, you can end the current session in the app and immediately start a new one.\n\n
&lt;img loading="lazy" src="/images/wechat/25e1c194ea9b.jpg"&gt;
\n\n
&lt;img loading="lazy" src="/images/wechat/f6c8463d69cf.jpg"&gt;
\n\n### EasyPark: A Must-Have for European Road Trips\n\nEasyPark is ideal for users who frequently travel across European countries. It covers multiple European nations, making it especially suitable for cross-border road trips.\n\n&lt;strong&gt;EasyPark&amp;rsquo;s Key Features:&lt;/strong&gt;\n\n* &lt;strong&gt;Cross-Border Coverage&lt;/strong&gt;: One app for multiple European countries, saving you the hassle of downloading different apps.\n* &lt;strong&gt;Real-Time Parking Search&lt;/strong&gt;: Quickly find available parking spots nearby.\n* &lt;strong&gt;Flexible Billing&lt;/strong&gt;: Pay only for the actual time you park. Start and stop sessions as you go.\n* &lt;strong&gt;Smart Reminders&lt;/strong&gt;: Avoid fines for overstaying your parking time.\n\n&lt;strong&gt;Best for&lt;/strong&gt;: Users who frequently take road trips across European countries.\n\n## 2. Money-Saving Tips for Long-Term Airport Parking: Parkos\n\nThe Parkos website specializes in consolidating information from multiple long-term parking lots near airports, offering secure, convenient, and affordable parking solutions.\n\n&lt;strong&gt;Advantages of Parkos:&lt;/strong&gt;\n\n* &lt;strong&gt;Transparent and Competitive Pricing&lt;/strong&gt;: Compare prices from various parking lots near the airport to quickly find the best deal.\n* &lt;strong&gt;Variety of Services&lt;/strong&gt;: Includes indoor and outdoor parking, shuttle bus transfers, and valet services.\n* &lt;strong&gt;Convenient Online Booking&lt;/strong&gt;: Book online in advance to avoid waiting in line.\n* &lt;strong&gt;Guaranteed Security&lt;/strong&gt;: Partner parking lots are thoroughly vetted for safety and reliability.\n\n### How to Use Parkos:\n\n1. Visit the official website: parkos.es\n2. Enter the airport name and your parking dates to see available options.\n3. Compare the prices and services of different parking lots to choose the most suitable one.\n4. Pay online and receive your booking confirmation.\n\n&lt;strong&gt;Best for&lt;/strong&gt;: Travelers who need long-term parking near the airport.\n\n
&lt;img loading="lazy" src="/images/wechat/a2ab1bc043df.jpg"&gt;
\n\n## Summary\n\nWhether you&amp;rsquo;re dealing with daily city parking or long-term airport parking in Spain, Telpark, EasyPark, and Parkos can help you solve your parking problems easily, saving you money and hassle.\n\nBookmark these useful apps and websites now to enjoy a convenient parking experience in Spain!\n\n&amp;mdash;\n\n&lt;strong&gt;List of Useful Articles:&lt;/strong&gt;\n\n* &lt;a href="https://mp.weixin.qq.com/s?__biz=MzkxNjY1NTM4NA==&amp;amp;mid=2247484060&amp;amp;idx=1&amp;amp;sn=5fc307cc3c8b57f7d5400d50205afcf5&amp;amp;scene=21#wechat_redirect"&gt;A Comprehensive Comparison of Basic Education in Spain: What Chinese Parents Should Know&lt;/a&gt;\n* &lt;a href="https://mp.weixin.qq.com/s?__biz=MzkxNjY1NTM4NA==&amp;amp;mid=2247484052&amp;amp;idx=1&amp;amp;sn=fddf7702ee9399b870bb76f3bc77ade5&amp;amp;scene=21#wechat_redirect"&gt;Income Analysis of Locals in Spain (Madrid vs. Beijing: Who Can Live a More Decent Life?)&lt;/a&gt;\n* &lt;a href="https://mp.weixin.qq.com/s?__biz=MzkxNjY1NTM4NA==&amp;amp;mid=2247484047&amp;amp;idx=1&amp;amp;sn=a974430b1d2bab78a86dff5850fd150d&amp;amp;scene=21#wechat_redirect"&gt;The Downsides of Living in Spain: A Detailed 2024 Comparison of Madrid vs. Beijing&lt;/a&gt;\n* &lt;a href="https://mp.weixin.qq.com/s?__biz=MzkxNjY1NTM4NA==&amp;amp;mid=2247484007&amp;amp;idx=1&amp;amp;sn=651c2c1e3125265bed56d430d8dd1eb1&amp;amp;scene=21#wechat_redirect"&gt;Experience with the Spanish Driving Road Test&lt;/a&gt;\n* &lt;a href="https://mp.weixin.qq.com/s?__biz=MzkxNjY1NTM4NA==&amp;amp;mid=2247483985&amp;amp;idx=1&amp;amp;sn=425bb166c57d434b0f1e486853978e84&amp;amp;scene=21#wechat_redirect"&gt;How to Self-Study Efficiently and Quickly Pass the Spanish Category B Driver&amp;rsquo;s License Theory Test&lt;/a&gt;\n* &lt;a href="https://mp.weixin.qq.com/s?__biz=MzkxNjY1NTM4NA==&amp;amp;mid=2247483927&amp;amp;idx=1&amp;amp;sn=e8c966f144638050bf4d6cae2019343c&amp;amp;scene=21#wechat_redirect"&gt;DIY Guide for Spain&amp;rsquo;s Non-Lucrative Visa Application - Checklist - Form Filling Instructions (3rd Edition)&lt;/a&gt;\n* &lt;a href="https://mp.weixin.qq.com/s?__biz=MzkxNjY1NTM4NA==&amp;amp;mid=2247483767&amp;amp;idx=1&amp;amp;sn=9de45907589d4100fec06836c7592c99&amp;amp;scene=21#wechat_redirect"&gt;DIY Tutorial for Renewing Spain&amp;rsquo;s Non-Lucrative Residency (Detailed Long-Form Article)&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;
}&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>```json</title><link>/en/xi-ban-ya-jia-zhao-lu-kao-jing-yan/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/xi-ban-ya-jia-zhao-lu-kao-jing-yan/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;{
&amp;ldquo;title&amp;rdquo;: &amp;ldquo;My Experience Passing the Spanish Driving Road Test&amp;rdquo;,
&amp;ldquo;body&amp;rdquo;: &amp;ldquo;I passed my road test, and I&amp;rsquo;m here to share my experience.\n\nDuring the driving road test in Spain, the examiner will only give instructions in Spanish, and the instructor is generally not allowed to translate. Therefore, it is crucial to master the following common Spanish commands and their expressions:\n\n* &lt;strong&gt;Start the engine&lt;/strong&gt;: Arrancar\n* &lt;strong&gt;Turn right&lt;/strong&gt;: Derecha\n* &lt;strong&gt;Turn left&lt;/strong&gt;: Izquierda\n* &lt;strong&gt;Go straight&lt;/strong&gt;: Recto\n* &lt;strong&gt;Make a U-turn&lt;/strong&gt;: Cambio de sentido\n* &lt;strong&gt;Indirect left turn&lt;/strong&gt;: izquierda indirecto\n* &lt;strong&gt;Roundabout&lt;/strong&gt;: Rotonda\n* &lt;strong&gt;First exit&lt;/strong&gt;: Primera salida\n* &lt;strong&gt;Second exit&lt;/strong&gt;: Segunda salida\n* &lt;strong&gt;Third exit&lt;/strong&gt;: Tercera salida\n* &lt;strong&gt;Fourth exit&lt;/strong&gt;: Cuarta salida\n* &lt;strong&gt;Stop&lt;/strong&gt;: Parar\n* &lt;strong&gt;Park&lt;/strong&gt;: Aparcar\n\nIf you don&amp;rsquo;t hear an instruction clearly, you can ask the examiner to repeat it in Spanish, for example: &amp;quot;Por favor repita&amp;quot;.\n\n### &lt;strong&gt;Be Aware of Deviations in the Examiner&amp;rsquo;s Instructions&lt;/strong&gt;\n\nSometimes the examiner may give an incorrect instruction, either intentionally or unintentionally. For example, if instructed to turn right but there is a traffic sign at the intersection or on the road prohibiting a right turn, you should ignore the instruction and continue to follow the road signs.\n\nAt the same time, you should maintain a wide field of vision while driving. Note that road guidance markings are often about 30 meters before an intersection, and there may be no corresponding signs at the intersection itself. Also, pay attention to vertical signs and traffic lights, with traffic lights having the highest priority. If there is a STOP sign at an intersection but also a green light, you must strictly follow the higher-priority traffic light and not stop.\n\n### &lt;strong&gt;Understanding Roundabout Rules&lt;/strong&gt;\n\n* &lt;strong&gt;Roundabouts within the city:&lt;/strong&gt;\n * For left turns and U-turns, you must use the inner lane.\n * When the inner lane has a traffic light, you can proceed directly on a green light. A flashing yellow light means you must yield to traffic from the right. Be sure to look to your right; if a car is 25 meters away, you must yield because it is approaching quickly.\n * For right turns and going straight, you should choose the outer lane.\n\n* &lt;strong&gt;Roundabouts outside the city:&lt;/strong&gt;\n * Always use the outer lane, unless you are overtaking, in which case you can use the inner lane.\n\nWhen exiting a roundabout, be sure to signal right in advance and use your turn signals correctly to assist with lane changes. If traffic congestion prevents you from changing from the inner lane to exit the roundabout, you should continue to circle until you can change lanes safely, and then switch to the rightmost lane (the further right, the better) to exit (in Spain, consecutive lane changes are allowed). For roundabouts that are split into several islands, enter from the rightmost lane for a left turn, and choose the middle or leftmost lane to go straight. The keyword is &lt;em&gt;indirecto&lt;/em&gt;.\n\n### &lt;strong&gt;Lane Selection and Intersection Driving&lt;/strong&gt;\n\n* &lt;strong&gt;When going straight:&lt;/strong&gt;\n * If there are three lanes, you should generally choose the first lane from the right.\n * If there are more than three lanes, it is recommended to use the second lane.\n\n* &lt;strong&gt;When passing through intersections:&lt;/strong&gt;\n * Avoid stopping on pedestrian crossings, bike lanes, or other special lanes, especially in congested areas marked with a cross-hatched grid.\n * If the vehicle in front of you stops due to lack of space, you should stop early and wait, ensuring your stopping position does not obstruct special lanes.\n\n### &lt;strong&gt;Safe Driving and Right-of-Way Awareness&lt;/strong&gt;\n\nSpanish traffic laws are very strict about the right-of-way. People have a strong sense of right-of-way. On crosswalks without traffic lights, pedestrians have absolute priority; they are not in the habit of looking left and right for traffic and may cross suddenly. Therefore, when driving in areas where you do not have the right-of-way, you must remain highly alert, especially in sections with yield signs. You need to check for approaching traffic in bicycle lanes or motor vehicle lanes behind you and turn your head to confirm the road conditions.\n\nHowever, with a green light, even if there are pedestrians on the crosswalk, the driver must not slow down or stop in advance, unless there is an unavoidable emergency, in which case only emergency braking is permitted. When passing a crosswalk without a traffic light, you should slow down appropriately. If there is a sign indicating students or children, you must also perform a braking action to slow down.\n\nGenerally, the speed limit on urban roads is 50 km/h, while single-lane roads may be limited to 30 or 20 km/h. Roads outside the city are generally 90 km/h, and highways are 120 km/h. You are generally required to drive as close to the maximum speed limit as possible; even exceeding it by 2-5 km/h is acceptable.\n\n### &lt;strong&gt;STOP Signs and Temporary Stopping Requirements&lt;/strong&gt;\n\nWhen you encounter a STOP line on the road, you must stop before the line and wait for 3 seconds, then stop again about 1-2 meters past the line to observe the traffic conditions. This double stop is a test requirement. If visibility is poor, you should stop multiple times to confirm safety.\n\nBut be aware: if there is also a traffic light, you must strictly follow the light&amp;rsquo;s signal. You are not allowed to stop at a green light; you must proceed directly. Stopping in this situation is actually a fault. If there is no stop line, position the front of your car about one meter into the intersection, stop for at least 3 seconds, and then proceed after confirming it is safe.\n\n### &lt;strong&gt;Road Test Procedure and Driving Strategy&lt;/strong&gt;\n\nThe road test usually begins with 3-5 minutes of independent driving, after which the examiner will give instructions. Since you may not be familiar with many of the roads on your first drive, it is advisable to observe road signs from a distance. For example, entering a roundabout might require you to be in the left lane, while the right lane is for other directions; this is usually indicated by traffic signs above the intersection. Sometimes, a left turn does not necessarily mean using the left lane; you might need to make the turn from the right lane. In such cases, you need to observe the road markings or overhead signs in advance and prepare to change lanes. If it&amp;rsquo;s too late to change lanes safely, it&amp;rsquo;s better to disobey the examiner&amp;rsquo;s instruction than to make a forced lane change.\n\nIf road guidance markings are difficult to see because they are blocked by large vehicles or are faded, and there are no clear directional or prohibitive signs at the intersection, you can sometimes look for hand signals from your instructor. When in doubt, it is generally safer to choose to turn right and try to avoid turning left.\n\n
&lt;img loading="lazy" src="/images/wechat/b8469f50e5d2.jpg"&gt;
\n\n&amp;gt; The road sign above indicates entering the roundabout from the left lane.\n\n
&lt;img loading="lazy" src="/images/wechat/e13d835e1a4d.jpg"&gt;
\n\n&amp;gt; Prioritize the traffic light on the right; do not stop at a green light.\n\n
&lt;img loading="lazy" src="/images/wechat/35d3cf03f638.jpg"&gt;
\n\n&amp;gt; The road markings indicate a right turn only, but there is no sign at the intersection prohibiting a left turn. Therefore, it&amp;rsquo;s difficult to see that a left turn is not allowed if a large vehicle is blocking the view.\n\n
&lt;img loading="lazy" src="/images/wechat/d58308650bda.jpg"&gt;
\n\n
&lt;img loading="lazy" src="/images/wechat/0148c0d9afcf.jpg"&gt;
\n\n&amp;gt; Two ways to navigate a roundabout&amp;rdquo;
}&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>```json</title><link>/en/chulilla-xuan-ya-xiao-zhen-tu-bu-lu-xian-fen-xiang-6-gong-li-chuan-yue-qian-nian-shi-kong/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/chulilla-xuan-ya-xiao-zhen-tu-bu-lu-xian-fen-xiang-6-gong-li-chuan-yue-qian-nian-shi-kong/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;{
&amp;ldquo;title&amp;rdquo;: &amp;ldquo;A Hiking Route in Chulilla, the Cliff Town: A 6km Journey Through a Millennium&amp;rdquo;,
&amp;ldquo;body&amp;rdquo;: &amp;ldquo;2025-01-28 23:52 Spain\n\n
&lt;img loading="lazy" src="/images/wechat/adc4be0a4441.jpg"&gt;
\n\n- &lt;strong&gt;📍Starting Point&lt;/strong&gt;: Town parking lot (39.6599279, -0.8916659)\n- &lt;strong&gt;⏱️Duration&lt;/strong&gt;: 3 hours\n\n&amp;mdash;\n\n1. &lt;strong&gt;Valley Exploration&lt;/strong&gt;:\n From the fork (39.6572005, -0.8921885), delve into the emerald river valley to reach the hidden Blue Lagoon (Charco Azul) (39.6650017, -0.8922144)\n\n2. &lt;strong&gt;Rope-Climbing to Caves + Hanging Bridges&lt;/strong&gt;,\n Return to the fork via the bridges above the river.\n\n3. &lt;strong&gt;Canyon Wonders&lt;/strong&gt;:\n From the back mountain entrance (39.6572988, -0.8929979), loop around to the other side of the town (39.6546164, -0.8941087)\n\n4. &lt;strong&gt;Via the chapel&lt;/strong&gt; (39.6557441, -0.8931008) &lt;strong&gt;leading directly to the medieval castle&lt;/strong&gt; (39.6558496, -0.8933849)(39.6558496, -0.8933849)&amp;rdquo;
}&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>A Comprehensive Comparison of Basic Education in Spain: The Truth Chinese Parents Should Know</title><link>/en/xi-ban-ya-ji-chu-jiao-yu-quan-jing-dui-bi-zhong-guo-jia-zhang-gai-zhi-dao-de-zhen-xiang/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/xi-ban-ya-ji-chu-jiao-yu-quan-jing-dui-bi-zhong-guo-jia-zhang-gai-zhi-dao-de-zhen-xiang/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Spain has a free and compulsory education system for ages 6 to 16, covering 6 years of primary school and 4 years of middle school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="-school-hours-and-tuition-differences"&gt;📚 School Hours and Tuition Differences&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spanish Public Schools&lt;/strong&gt;: School hours are from 9:00 AM to 2:00 PM, with 4 classes per day. It&amp;rsquo;s free.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spanish Private and International Schools&lt;/strong&gt;: School hours are typically from 9:00 AM to 4:00 PM, with 6 classes per day.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The median tuition for private schools is approximately €6,000/year (about 50,000 RMB).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;International schools cost around €8,000/year (about 70,000 RMB).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are significant variations based on grade level, region, and school, with costs potentially differing by a factor of 1-2.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="-teaching-staff-and-pedagogical-features"&gt;🏫 Teaching Staff and Pedagogical Features&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Teacher absenteeism is relatively high in Spain. A doctor&amp;rsquo;s note for sick leave is legally binding and can be issued over the phone for paid sick leave.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Primary schools generally use a &amp;ldquo;generalist&amp;rdquo; system, where a single teacher teaches multiple subjects like English, math, humanities, science, art, and physical education, limiting subject-specific expertise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subject-specific teaching only begins in middle school.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The saying &amp;ldquo;the gym teacher taught my math&amp;rdquo; is not a joke in Spain; it&amp;rsquo;s a result of the generalist system in primary schools.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exam scores are not ranked.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="-language-of-instruction-and-multilingual-environment"&gt;🈯 Language of Instruction and Multilingual Environment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;International schools primarily use English for instruction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Private and public schools mainly use Spanish.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Autonomous communities like Valencia and Catalonia require students to learn the local language.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In middle school, a second foreign language like French or German is added, making the multilingual workload heavy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="-workload-and-holiday-schedule"&gt;📖 Workload and Holiday Schedule&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is less homework.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The academic year is divided into three terms, with a total of about 160–180 instructional days.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Holidays are long.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="-comparison-with-basic-education-in-china"&gt;🇨🇳 Comparison with Basic Education in China&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Public Schools&lt;/strong&gt;: School hours are from 8:00 AM to 4:00 PM, with 6–8 classes per day. It&amp;rsquo;s free, with some regions offering after-school programs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Private/International Schools&lt;/strong&gt;: 8:00 AM to 5:30 PM, with evening self-study sessions starting in middle school, which do not exist in Spain.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Private: Approx. 60,000 RMB/year&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;International: Approx. 180,000 RMB/year&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The academic year is divided into two semesters, with over 190 instructional days.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="-disparity-in-campus-facilities"&gt;🏟️ Disparity in Campus Facilities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;International schools in China often boast campuses of over 100 acres, featuring heated swimming pools, theaters, multimedia libraries, maker labs, Olympic-standard stadiums, and even equestrian centers, golf courses, and drone and robotics labs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In contrast, Spanish schools are modest and compact, with simple facilities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="-curriculum-and-difficulty"&gt;📘 Curriculum and Difficulty&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people believe that primary school math in China is much harder than abroad, but this is a long-standing misconception.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>A Summer Road Trip in Northern Spain: From Valencia to Covadonga</title><link>/en/xi-ban-ya-shu-jia-bei-bu-zi-jia-zhi-lv-cong-wa-lun-xi-ya-dao-ke-wa-dong-jia/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/xi-ban-ya-shu-jia-bei-bu-zi-jia-zhi-lv-cong-wa-lun-xi-ya-dao-ke-wa-dong-jia/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Last summer, I completed a 10-day grand road trip loop through northern Spain. &lt;strong&gt;Starting from Valencia, I traveled through Zaragoza, Olite, Bilbao, Santander, Comillas, Covadonga, Salamanca, Ávila, and Madrid, finally returning to Valencia after lunch in the cliff town of Cuenca.&lt;/strong&gt; This journey offered a mix of cities, ancient castles, mountains, the sea, and delicious food. We were a group of four, and this article shares all the details of our trip for anyone who might find it useful.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>An Overview of European Ethnogenesis: A Long-Term Process of Migration, Language Replacement, and Institutional Integration</title><link>/en/ou-zhou-min-zu-yan-hua-gai-shu-qian-xi-yu-yan-ti-huan-yu-zhi-du-zheng-he-de-chang-qi-guo-cheng/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/ou-zhou-min-zu-yan-hua-gai-shu-qian-xi-yu-yan-ti-huan-yu-zhi-du-zheng-he-de-chang-qi-guo-cheng/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The ethnic structure of Europe was not fixed from antiquity but was gradually formed through a long historical process of &lt;strong&gt;prehistoric population migrations, language replacement, political conquests, and religious integration&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is a梳理 of the main stages and structural features of European ethnogenesis in &lt;strong&gt;chronological order&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id="i-neolithic-era-near-eastern-agricultural-peoples-enter-europe"&gt;I. Neolithic Era: Near Eastern Agricultural Peoples Enter Europe&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(c. 7000–5000 BC)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Origin&lt;/strong&gt;
Near Eastern Fertile Crescent, Anatolia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Paternal Haplogroup Characteristics&lt;/strong&gt;
Represented by &lt;strong&gt;J haplogroup (especially J2)&lt;/strong&gt; (not the only one, but a significant proportion in the early agricultural diffusion)&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Ancient China: A Civilization That Once Left Europe Far Behind</title><link>/en/gu-dai-zhong-guo-qi-shi-ceng-rang-zheng-ge-ou-zhou-wang-chen-mo-ji/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/gu-dai-zhong-guo-qi-shi-ceng-rang-zheng-ge-ou-zhou-wang-chen-mo-ji/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;We are accustomed to thinking that &amp;ldquo;the West has always been ahead of China,&amp;rdquo; but this is actually a historical illusion shaped in reverse by the outcome of the Industrial Revolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="i-the-rear-view-mirror-illusion-of-history"&gt;I. The &amp;ldquo;Rear-View Mirror&amp;rdquo; Illusion of History&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, many Chinese people have an almost unconscious belief: &lt;strong&gt;the West seems inherently more advanced than China.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this is a typical historical illusion, &amp;ldquo;reverse-engineered&amp;rdquo; by the outcome of the Industrial Revolution.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Answering Philosophical Questions with Science: A Rational Reconstruction of Time, Meaning, Consciousness, Causality, and Morality</title><link>/en/yong-ke-xue-hui-da-na-xie-zhe-xue-wen-ti-guan-yu-shi-jian-yi-yi-yi-shi-yin-guo-yu-dao-de-de-li-xing-zhong-gou/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/yong-ke-xue-hui-da-na-xie-zhe-xue-wen-ti-guan-yu-shi-jian-yi-yi-yi-shi-yin-guo-yu-dao-de-de-li-xing-zhong-gou/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Throughout human history, a certain class of questions has been asked repeatedly for millennia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is time?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does life have meaning?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Must we fear death?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do we truly have free will?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where do good and evil truly come from?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These questions have long been categorized under &amp;lsquo;philosophy&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;metaphysics,&amp;rsquo; shrouded in layers of myth, religion, metaphor, and strong emotion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But today, with the advancements in physics, neuroscience, and information theory, we have the opportunity for the first time to—&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Does AI Have Memory?</title><link>/en/ai-you-ji-yi-ma/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/ai-you-ji-yi-ma/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;When many people use an AI chatbot for the first time, they might feel like it &amp;ldquo;remembers&amp;rdquo; what was said before. For example, if you ask a question and then follow up on it a little later, it can still connect the dots. This leads to a common question: Does AI actually have memory?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s get to the conclusion first: An AI&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;memory&amp;rdquo; is not the same as the archival memory we might imagine. It relies on predicting with parameter weights, not on hard-drive-style storage.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Europe Once 'Lost' an Entire Civilization—Why Did Ancient Greek Rational Knowledge Disappear in Medieval Europe?</title><link>/en/ou-zhou-ceng-jing-nong-diu-guo-zheng-ge-wen-ming-gu-xi-la-li-xing-zhi-shi-wei-he-zai-zhong-shi-ji-ou-zhou-xiao-shi/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/ou-zhou-ceng-jing-nong-diu-guo-zheng-ge-wen-ming-gu-xi-la-li-xing-zhi-shi-wei-he-zai-zhong-shi-ji-ou-zhou-xiao-shi/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In medieval Christian Europe, a linguistic divide, the collapse of the educational system, and religious monopoly led to a systematic interruption of Greek mathematics, philosophy, and science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conversely, Greek knowledge was fully preserved, translated, and developed in the Byzantine and Islamic worlds, eventually returning to Europe through cross-civilizational transfer, igniting the Renaissance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people might subconsciously assume that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since Europe is the successor to ancient Greece and Rome,
its mathematics, philosophy, and science
should have been naturally passed down through the ages.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>From Abraham's Family Drama to the Global 'One God'</title><link>/en/cong-ya-bo-la-han-de-jia-shi-dao-ying-xiang-quan-qiu-de-wei-yi-shen/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/cong-ya-bo-la-han-de-jia-shi-dao-ying-xiang-quan-qiu-de-wei-yi-shen/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In the early days of human civilization, religion was like a chaotic &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;startup competition&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, our ancestors, out of fear,
called the thunder &amp;ldquo;father&amp;rdquo;
and the rain &amp;ldquo;mother,&amp;rdquo;
creating the primitive worship of animism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later—&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ancient Egyptians deified their pets (jackals, cats).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ancient Greeks, on the other hand, raised a bunch of &amp;ldquo;superpowered man-children&amp;rdquo; on Mount Olympus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zeus and his family,
besides not doing any real work,
were busy having affairs and bickering every day.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>From Emergence to Intelligent Phase Transition: How Large Language Models Sense High-Dimensional Spaces</title><link>/en/cong-yong-xian-dao-zhi-neng-xiang-bian-da-yu-yan-mo-xing-ru-he-gan-ying-gao-wei-kong-jian/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/cong-yong-xian-dao-zhi-neng-xiang-bian-da-yu-yan-mo-xing-ru-he-gan-ying-gao-wei-kong-jian/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;When the massive parameters of a large language model intertwine into a web in information space, the &amp;lsquo;intelligence&amp;rsquo; it exhibits is not a mysterious consciousness, but a natural product of emergence, self-organization, and high-dimensional information structures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And inspiration, perhaps, is merely the projection of a &lt;strong&gt;quantum fluctuation in a six-dimensional space&lt;/strong&gt; onto our four-dimensional spacetime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are always amazed by the &amp;lsquo;cleverness&amp;rsquo; of AI—&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It can write articles, reason, and code, sometimes even creating the illusion:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Hiking Route Recommendation — Garbi</title><link>/en/tu-bu-lu-xian-tui-jian-jia-lei-bi-garbi/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/tu-bu-lu-xian-tui-jian-jia-lei-bi-garbi/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Please provide the body of the article that needs to be optimized, and I will format it in Markdown according to your requirements.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>How to Apply for a Spanish Fishing License Online</title><link>/en/ru-he-zai-xian-shen-qing-xi-ban-ya-diao-yu-xu-ke-zheng/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/ru-he-zai-xian-shen-qing-xi-ban-ya-diao-yu-xu-ke-zheng/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In Spain, fishing licenses are mainly divided into two categories: &lt;strong&gt;sea fishing licenses&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;river (freshwater) fishing licenses&lt;/strong&gt;. This article will provide a detailed guide on how to apply for both types of licenses online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id="i-sea-fishing-license-application-process"&gt;I. Sea Fishing License Application Process&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The application process for sea fishing licenses is relatively uniform across different regions in Spain. You can apply directly online through the official website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="-official-website-for-sea-fishing-licenses"&gt;🔗 Official Website for Sea Fishing Licenses&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Application URL:
&lt;a href="https://www.gva.es/es/inicio/procedimientos?id_proc=647&amp;amp;id_caso=sollicitud#presentacion"&gt;https://www.gva.es/es/inicio/procedimientos?id_proc=647&amp;id_caso=sollicitud#presentacion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>How to Apply Online for a Collective Residence Certificate for a Minor</title><link>/en/ru-he-zai-xian-wei-wei-cheng-nian-ren-shen-qing-ji-ti-zhu-zhi-zheng-ming/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/ru-he-zai-xian-wei-wei-cheng-nian-ren-shen-qing-ji-ti-zhu-zhi-zheng-ming/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In Spain, the residence certificate (empadronamiento) is one of the most commonly used official documents, widely required for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Residency renewal for minors (renovación del menor)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;School registration / transfer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Health card (SIP) application&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Applying for family benefits, childcare assistance, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a child is involved, the standard requirement is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Certificado de empadronamiento colectivo (Collective Residence Certificate)&lt;/strong&gt;
This document proves that the child lives with their parents/guardians and is the only valid document recognized by all government departments.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>How to Self-Study Efficiently and Quickly Pass the Spanish B Driving License Theory Test</title><link>/en/ru-he-gao-xiao-zi-xue-kuai-su-tong-guo-xi-ban-ya-qi-che-jia-shi-zhi-zhao-b-de-li-lun-kao-shi/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/ru-he-gao-xiao-zi-xue-kuai-su-tong-guo-xi-ban-ya-qi-che-jia-shi-zhi-zhao-b-de-li-lun-kao-shi/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="i-study-method-for-the-theory-test"&gt;I. Study Method for the Theory Test&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is highly inadvisable to just cram practice questions because:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The question bank is huge. The English test has over 200 sets, each with 30 questions, totaling more than 6,000 questions. Finishing them all is time-consuming and exhausting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The translations and questions in the bank may not be accurate, and the answers could be wrong.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The actual exam questions are not directly from the question bank, so finishing it is not very helpful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The knowledge in the question bank is fragmented and not systematic. Without systematic learning, you might not be able to answer if the question is phrased differently.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Efficient Study Method:&lt;/strong&gt; Since I took the exam in English, the following content is based on English materials.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>If I 'Die' Once Every Day, Does My Life Still Have Meaning?</title><link>/en/ru-guo-mei-tian-du-hui-si-yi-ci-wo-huo-zhe-hai-you-yi-yi-ma/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/ru-guo-mei-tian-du-hui-si-yi-ci-wo-huo-zhe-hai-you-yi-yi-ma/</guid><description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Foreword:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If one day you discover that &amp;lsquo;you&amp;rsquo; can be perfectly replicated, does your current existence still have meaning?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As AI&amp;rsquo;s logic and reasoning gradually approach or even surpass human capabilities, we may have to confront a cruel yet rational fact: consciousness might not be a soul, but rather a &amp;lsquo;model&amp;rsquo; that is currently running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id="i-defining-consciousness-the-ultimatum-from-ai"&gt;I. Defining Consciousness: The &amp;lsquo;Ultimatum&amp;rsquo; from AI&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before discussing &amp;lsquo;who am I,&amp;rsquo; we must first let go of the sanctified image of the self.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Income Analysis for Locals in Spain (Madrid vs. Beijing: Who Can Afford a More Decent Life?)</title><link>/en/xi-ban-ya-ben-di-ren-shou-ru-fen-xi-ma-de-li-vs-bei-jing-shui-geng-neng-guo-shang-ti-mian-sheng-huo/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/xi-ban-ya-ben-di-ren-shou-ru-fen-xi-ma-de-li-vs-bei-jing-shui-geng-neng-guo-shang-ti-mian-sheng-huo/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;My previous article, &lt;a href="https://mp.weixin.qq.com/s?__biz=MzkxNjY1NTM4NA==&amp;amp;mid=2247484047&amp;amp;idx=1&amp;amp;sn=a974430b1d2bab78a86dff5850fd150d&amp;amp;scene=21#wechat_redirect"&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Downsides of Living in Spain: A Detailed 2024 Comparison of Madrid vs. Beijing&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, sparked considerable debate despite objectively presenting the cost of living in Spain with reliable data. One commenter asked, &amp;ldquo;Why not compare the income of Spanish locals? For them, these prices are nothing.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, let&amp;rsquo;s complete the picture today: &lt;strong&gt;What are the income levels in Madrid and Beijing really like? We&amp;rsquo;ll cover high-income earners, blue-collar workers, and post-tax disposable income all in one go.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Learning Spanish Made Me Realize Why Chinese is the Most "Scientific" Language</title><link>/en/wei-shen-me-shuo-zhong-wen-cai-shi-zui-ke-xue-de-yu-yan-zheng-zai-xue-xi-yu-de-wo-zhong-yu-ming-bai-le/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/wei-shen-me-shuo-zhong-wen-cai-shi-zui-ke-xue-de-yu-yan-zheng-zai-xue-xi-yu-de-wo-zhong-yu-ming-bai-le/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;No verb conjugations, no grammatical gender, and highly efficient and precise expression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The logical beauty of Chinese is not just something to marvel at, but something to be confident about.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id="-some-confidence-we-really-should-express-loudly"&gt;🇨🇳 Some Confidence We Really Should Express Loudly&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Living abroad these past two years, I&amp;rsquo;ve often heard some Chinese friends &lt;strong&gt;disparage their own mother tongue and culture&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Chinese people aren&amp;rsquo;t as beautiful as white people.&amp;rdquo;
&amp;ldquo;Chinese people have always been uncivilized.&amp;rdquo;
&amp;ldquo;The Chinese diet is too eclectic.&amp;rdquo;
&amp;ldquo;Our language lacks class; it&amp;rsquo;s not as sophisticated as English.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Same Symptoms, Different Causes: Don't Let Intuition Delay Your Treatment</title><link>/en/zheng-zhuang-xiang-tong-bing-yin-bu-tong-bie-rang-zhi-jue-dan-wu-le-zhi-liao/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/zheng-zhuang-xiang-tong-bing-yin-bu-tong-bie-rang-zhi-jue-dan-wu-le-zhi-liao/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;We often say, &amp;ldquo;Get treated promptly when you&amp;rsquo;re sick,&amp;rdquo; but often, the real issue isn&amp;rsquo;t about being &amp;ldquo;prompt&amp;rdquo; but about being &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;correct.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When many people feel unwell, their first reaction is to judge based on experience:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;🧠 &amp;ldquo;Stuffy nose? Must be rhinitis.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;🧠 &amp;ldquo;Coughing? It&amp;rsquo;s just a cold.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;🧠 &amp;ldquo;Headache? I&amp;rsquo;ll just take a painkiller.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then they start self-diagnosing and self-medicating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in reality, &lt;strong&gt;many different illnesses can present with the exact same symptoms.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Spain Non-Lucrative Visa Renewal Online Submission (EX01) - Complete Step-by-Step Guide for a Family of Three (Including Minors)</title><link>/en/xi-ban-ya-fei-ying-li-xu-qian-xian-shang-di-qian-ex01-yi-jia-san-kou-wan-zheng-shi-cao-liu-cheng-han-wei-cheng-nian-ren/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/xi-ban-ya-fei-ying-li-xu-qian-xian-shang-di-qian-ex01-yi-jia-san-kou-wan-zheng-shi-cao-liu-cheng-han-wei-cheng-nian-ren/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="1-submission-time-requirements"&gt;1. Submission Time Requirements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: left"&gt;Item&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: left"&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Earliest Submission Time&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;60 days&lt;/strong&gt; before NIE expiration&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;Latest Submission Time&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: left"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Within 90 days&lt;/strong&gt; after NIE expiration&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h3 id="financial-requirements-explanation"&gt;Financial Requirements Explanation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Non-lucrative visa renewal is for a &lt;strong&gt;2-year period&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One year requires &lt;strong&gt;4 times the IPREM, so two years require 8 times&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For each additional family member, an extra &lt;strong&gt;1x IPREM is needed for 1 year, and 2x for 2 years&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking the official 2025 figures as an example:
&lt;strong&gt;IPREM = €7,200 / year&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Distance from Beijing to Shanghai: LLM Text Vectorization and RAG-Enhanced Vector Databases</title><link>/en/bei-jing-dao-shang-hai-de-ju-li-da-yu-yan-mo-xing-de-wen-ben-xiang-liang-hua-he-rag-zeng-qiang-xiang-liang-shu-ju-ku/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/bei-jing-dao-shang-hai-de-ju-li-da-yu-yan-mo-xing-de-wen-ben-xiang-liang-hua-he-rag-zeng-qiang-xiang-liang-shu-ju-ku/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;We often say, &amp;ldquo;Large Language Models are very smart.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They can write articles, answer questions, code, and even perform some logical reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in reality, the principle behind this isn&amp;rsquo;t mysterious:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;👉 It just turns a piece of text into a string of numbers,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;👉 and then &amp;ldquo;calculates the distance&amp;rdquo; in a high-dimensional space.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This might sound a bit abstract, but with a small example, you&amp;rsquo;ll understand it right away 👇&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Downsides of Living in Spain: A Detailed 2024 Comparison of Madrid vs. Beijing</title><link>/en/xi-ban-ya-sheng-huo-de-que-dian-2024-nian-ma-de-li-vs-bei-jing-xiang-jin-dui-bi/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/xi-ban-ya-sheng-huo-de-que-dian-2024-nian-ma-de-li-vs-bei-jing-xiang-jin-dui-bi/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Spain has long been regarded as a country with a high quality of life in Europe, attracting numerous immigrants and international students. However, a side-by-side comparison with China, particularly its capital Beijing, reveals significant shortcomings in Spain across many core aspects of life. Based on the latest 2024 data, this article provides a systematic comparison between Madrid and Beijing, focusing on dimensions such as consumer costs, education, healthcare, transportation, housing, home appliances, automobiles, and public safety, to deeply uncover the various inconveniences and cost pressures of living in Spain.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Han Chinese: A 5,000-Year Legacy of Huaxia Bloodline and Culture</title><link>/en/han-zu-de-min-zu-xing-zhi-hua-xia-xue-mai-yu-zhong-hua-wen-hua-de-wu-qian-nian-chuan-cheng/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/han-zu-de-min-zu-xing-zhi-hua-xia-xue-mai-yu-zhong-hua-wen-hua-de-wu-qian-nian-chuan-cheng/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="i-mythical-beginnings-yan-huang-and-chiyou"&gt;I. Mythical Beginnings: Yan, Huang, and Chiyou&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Records in &lt;em&gt;Shiji&lt;/em&gt; (Records of the Grand Historian) and &lt;em&gt;Guoyu&lt;/em&gt; (Discourses of the States) state:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Yellow Emperor defeated the Yan Emperor at the Battle of Banquan, leading to the submission of the Yan tribe;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He then defeated Chiyou at the Battle of Zhuolu, ultimately emerging victorious.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not merely a legend but a symbol of the integration of ancient tribes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Yellow Emperor&amp;rsquo;s group&lt;/strong&gt;: An agricultural tribe from the Central Plains, with the surname Ji;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Yan Emperor&amp;rsquo;s group&lt;/strong&gt;: A tribe with the surname Jiang, related to the ancient Qiang people;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chiyou&amp;rsquo;s group&lt;/strong&gt;: The Jiuli tribe, ancestors of the Miao-Man peoples of the south.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, the people of the Yan Emperor and Chiyou were incorporated into the Yellow Emperor&amp;rsquo;s tribe, forming the &amp;ldquo;Huaxia.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Myth of the Thousand-Year Turtle: How Long Will We Keep Making Assumptions?</title><link>/en/qian-nian-wang-ba-wan-nian-gui-wo-men-dao-di-hai-yao-xiang-dang-ran-dao-ji-shi/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/qian-nian-wang-ba-wan-nian-gui-wo-men-dao-di-hai-yao-xiang-dang-ran-dao-ji-shi/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Almost everyone has heard the old saying, &amp;ldquo;A turtle for a thousand years, a tortoise for ten thousand.&amp;rdquo; In Chinese culture, turtles and tortoises are seen as symbols of longevity, as if they are naturally destined to outlive several human generations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But here&amp;rsquo;s the question: &lt;strong&gt;Are there really turtles that have lived for a thousand years?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people see a giant turtle or tortoise and exclaim, &amp;ldquo;Wow, this one must be hundreds of years old!&amp;rdquo; While such claims might &amp;ldquo;sound plausible,&amp;rdquo; they actually &lt;strong&gt;don&amp;rsquo;t stand up to the slightest scrutiny&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Pinnacle of Algorithms and the Source of Logic: When The Nine Chapters on the Mathematical Art Meets Euclid's Elements</title><link>/en/suan-fa-zhi-dian-yu-luo-ji-zhi-yuan-dang-jiu-zhang-suan-shu-yu-jian-ji-he-yuan-ben/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/suan-fa-zhi-dian-yu-luo-ji-zhi-yuan-dang-jiu-zhang-suan-shu-yu-jian-ji-he-yuan-ben/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;At the dawn of human civilization, two mathematical works emerged in almost the same era. Like two rivers flowing in different directions, they quietly shaped the &lt;strong&gt;completely different intellectual traditions&lt;/strong&gt; of the East and West.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One came from China,
one from ancient Greece.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;China&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Nine Chapters on the Mathematical Art&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ancient Greece&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong&gt;Euclid&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Elements&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To this day, our understanding of &lt;strong&gt;science, technology, and even artificial intelligence&lt;/strong&gt; still carries the DNA of these two books.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Truth About European Royalty: The Continent Was Ruled by Germans</title><link>/en/ou-zhou-wang-shi-de-zhen-xiang-tong-zhi-ge-guo-de-qi-shi-shi-yi-qun-de-yi-zhi-ren/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/ou-zhou-wang-shi-de-zhen-xiang-tong-zhi-ge-guo-de-qi-shi-shi-yi-qun-de-yi-zhi-ren/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Many people assume that,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The British royal family is British,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The French royal family is French,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the Spanish royal family is, naturally, Spanish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if you take even a brief look at the history of European royalty, you&amp;rsquo;ll discover a fact that seems absurd yet is entirely true—&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The core of the entire European royal system is almost entirely of German origin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not just a few here and there, but systematically.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Was the Ancient Chinese Imperial Examination Only About the Eight-Legged Essay? (The Earliest Exams Balanced Arts and Sciences)</title><link>/en/gu-dai-zhong-guo-de-ke-ju-zhi-du-zhi-you-ba-gu-wen-me-zui-zao-de-ke-ju-shi-wen-li-shuang-xiu/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/gu-dai-zhong-guo-de-ke-ju-zhi-du-zhi-you-ba-gu-wen-me-zui-zao-de-ke-ju-shi-wen-li-shuang-xiu/</guid><description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Historical and archaeological clarification:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The imperial examination system wasn&amp;rsquo;t just about the eight-legged essay; it originally balanced arts and sciences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The foundation of Han civilization&amp;rsquo;s belief system is reason and ethics, not theocracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Europe was consumed by faith, China had long revered science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id="many-people-think-the-ancient-imperial-examinations-only-tested-the-eight-legged-essay-and-that-scholars-were-all-bookworms"&gt;Many people think the ancient imperial examinations only tested the eight-legged essay, and that scholars were all &amp;ldquo;bookworms.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the truth is quite the opposite.
For a long time, the true imperial examination system was a &amp;ldquo;balance of arts and sciences.&amp;rdquo;
Ancient China was not just a land of poetry, books, rites, and music, but also a civilization that revered science and reason.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Why Did Europe Turn to Democracy? — The Republican Tradition, Not an Accidental Historical Choice</title><link>/en/ou-zhou-wei-he-hui-zou-xiang-min-zhu-gong-he-guo-chuan-tong-bing-fei-ou-ran-de-li-shi-xuan-ze/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 11:20:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>/en/ou-zhou-wei-he-hui-zou-xiang-min-zhu-gong-he-guo-chuan-tong-bing-fei-ou-ran-de-li-shi-xuan-ze/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;When people talk about European democracy, they often focus on a specific revolution or a particular declaration, as if democracy were an institutional innovation that suddenly appeared one day in the modern era.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if we look back through history, we find a more fundamental and often overlooked fact:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Europe did not suddenly learn republicanism;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;it had long lived with the political experience that “a republic could exist.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Europe, the republic was never a fleeting moment of inspiration, but an institutional tradition spanning more than two thousand years.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>